<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvord in season to the kingdom of England. Or, A precious cordiall for a distempered kingdom. Wherein are laid down things profitable, and usefull for all, and offensive to none that love the truth and peace. / By the meanest of the servants of Jesus Christ, M. Cary.</title>
            <author>Cary, Mary.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81088</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C739</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E393_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201606</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862106</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862106</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114255</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81088)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114255)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 62:E393[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvord in season to the kingdom of England. Or, A precious cordiall for a distempered kingdom. Wherein are laid down things profitable, and usefull for all, and offensive to none that love the truth and peace. / By the meanest of the servants of Jesus Christ, M. Cary.</title>
                  <author>Cary, Mary.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.W. for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the Black-spred Eagle at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114255:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Word in Seaſon TO THE KINGDOM OF <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> OR, A precious CORDIALL for a diſtempered KINGDOM. Wherein are laid down things profitable, and uſefull for all, and offenſive to none that love the Truth and Peace.</p>
            <p>By the meaneſt of the Servants of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>M. Cary.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>ISAIAH 48.17, 18, 19.</bibl>
               <p>Thus ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer, the Holy one of Iſrael; I am the Lord thy God which teacheth thee to profit, which leadeth thee by the way which thou ſhouldeſt go.</p>
               <p>O that thou hadſt hearkened unto my commandments: then had thy peace been as a river, and thy righteouſneſs as the waves of the ſea. Thy ſeed alſo had been as the ſand, and the off-ſpring of thy bowels like the gravel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: his name ſhould not have been cut off, nor deſtroyed from before me.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. W.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Black-ſpred Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114255:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoever thou art that readeſt the inſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, know, that if thou art one that art active in helping on of that which I call the poſitive part; then thou doeſt what lies in thee to bring happineſs, and tranquility to thy native Kingdom: and however it go with others, thou ſhalt ſurely reap the benefit of it, either internally, or externally, or both. But if thou art one that driveſt on the negative part, thou art one that endeavoureſt to drive on thine own ruine: and this I hope thou wilt plainly ſee in the peruſing of it: wherein I ſhould have been far more Copious, but knowing that generally brevity is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, I have endeavoured to ſay as little as could be ſpoken (if I ſaid any thing) in the things that are moſt generally acknowledged, and to be as compendious as I could in the things that are (though clear in themſelves) more ſtumbled at by ſome. Now therefore if thou wouldſt not be the contriver of thine own ruine, but deſireſt thine
<pb facs="tcp:114255:2"/>own and the Kingdomes proſperity; then deſire ſtrength from above, to overcome all the temptations under which thou art, and lay aſide all the deſignes which thou haſt on foot (in which it may be thou aimeſt at thine own outward advantage) wherein thou croſſeſt all, or any of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, laid down in the poſitive part of this diſcourſe: ſo ſhalt thou have thy deſires ſatisfied, which that thou mayeſt obtain, is the aim, and fervent deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in any Chriſtian office of Love (however thou deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt with me) that lies in my Power. <hi>M. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114255:3"/>
            <head>A word in ſeaſon to the Kingdom OF <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great God, having wrought by his owne arme great deliverances for this Kingdome of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, doth doubtleſs now expect that Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land ſhould bring forth anſwerable fruit, when he had hedged, and fenced his vineyard, (<hi>Iſa</hi> 5.) and beſtowed choyce favours up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, he looked (ſaith the text <hi>ver.</hi> 4) that it ſhould bring forth grapes, and it brought forth wilde grapes. It were well for England if he had not juſt cauſe ſo to complaine of it. But that it may not be ſo, let all the people, from the higheſt to the loweſt, from the King that ſits upon the Throne, to him that ſits upon the Dunghill; let Parliament, and Synod, Citie and Country, attend to the inſuing diſcourſe (and let it ſinke deep into their ſpirits) which doth contain a Narration (wholly drawne from the Scriptures) of thoſe paths which (a nation walking in them) will be the readieſt way, and ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt cut to a happie and flouriſhing eſtate.</p>
            <p>But though this diſcourſe concerne all, and therfore in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall I call upon all to atend unto it; yet in a more peculiar man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I ſhall direct it to you Chaire-men (that is to ſay) you that ſit at the Sterne, you that are the heads and rulers of the people, and are in places of authoritie: for you are to act for the whole kingdome, and what is done by you is done by them: and either the benefit, or the evill of it will reflect upon the whole therefore to you in particular I ſhall direct my diſcourſe, and let all others obſerve ſo much of it as concerns them in their ſeverall places, and ſtations.</p>
            <p>But before I come to the poſitive part of my diſcourſe, to lay downe what thoſe paths are, which are the paths of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:114255:3"/>&amp;c. I ſhall firſt brieefly lay it downe negatively, what it is not, but what is the way to ruine (becauſe the Scripture ſo lay e it downe alſo) and ſhall then more largely lay downe the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive part, for the making of it moſt cleere, and perſpicuous to every eye, if poſible: and ſhall anſwer thoſe objections, which poſſibly ſome may make againſt it.</p>
            <p>As for the negative part. 1. Oppreſſion of the poor, &amp; ſuffering the violent man to afflict the needy, and the neglect of doing juſtice in their behalfe, is not the way to happineſs, but the way to ruine, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 12.5. for the oppreſſing of the poor, and for the ſighing of the needy, now will I ariſe ſaith the Lord, I will ſet him in ſafety <hi>&amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 5.7, 9. He looked for judgment, but behold oppreſſion; for righteouſneſſe, but behold acry: and what's the effect? In mine eares ſaid the Lord of hoſts, of a truth many houſes ſhall be deſolate, even great and faire, without inhabitant, when by unjuſt, and unreaſonable wayes, men ſhall pluck away the lands, or eſtates, or detaine the wages of the poor, and needy, or thoſe that in compariſon of themſelves are in a meane condition, on purpoſe to feather their own neſts, and to build them great and faire houſes; it is the ready paths to deſtruction, and to leave their houſes without inhabitant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The abounding of ſuch vices as theſe in a kingdome, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the due execution of juſtice upon them, is the way to bring in deſtruction upon a kingdome: as drunkenneſs, adultery, forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, ſwearing, <hi>&amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Woe to them that riſe up in the morning, that they may follow ſtrong drinke, that continue untill night, till wine inflame them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8. <hi>They committed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and fell in one day</hi> 23. <hi>thouſand, and becauſe of oaths the land mourns,</hi> ſaies the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To refuſe to ſtoope to the Scepter of Jeſus Chriſt, and not to admit of him as King: and conſequently, to receive all rules for worſhip from him, and to be governed by him in all ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all reſpects, but to follow the precepts and commandments of men therein, is the way to ruine: As for thoſe mine enemies that will not have me to raigne over them, bring them hither, and ſlay them before me.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The troubling, wronging, and oppreſſing the Saints of Ieſus Chriſt, is the way to ruine a kingdome. For he that toucheth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114255:4"/>them, toucheth the apple of Gods eye, and they are the props and pillars of a kingdome, and that kingdome that ſhall turne thoſe <hi>Lots</hi> out of it, whether it be by death, or by baniſhment, takes the way to ſet it ſelfe on fire, and to open a gap for a devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring enemie to come into it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And laſtly, That kingdome that ſhall ſay unto the Prophets, propheſie not, &amp; ſhall ſtop the mouths of thoſe which God hath opened to preach the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, &amp; ſhall charge them not to preach Chriſt any more; takes the way to ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for ſuch are fighters againſt God,<note place="margin">Acts 5 39.</note> &amp; it is hard for them to kick againſt the pricks<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let the potſherds ſtrive with the pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſherds of the earth,<note place="margin">Acts 9 5.</note> but as for thoſe that ſhall thus do, if they perſiſt in it, he will rule them with a rod of Iron, &amp; breake them in peeces like a potters veſſell; which when it is broken can never be made whole againe.</p>
            <p>And thus I have ſhewn what are the paths of deſtruction; &amp; now I come to lay downe poſitively what are the waies that bring proſperitie, and happineſſe to a kingdome: which I ſhall particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly preſent unto, &amp; preſs upon thoſe that are in places of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: becauſe what ſhall be done by them, is done for the whole.</p>
            <p>Be wiſe now therefore ye rulers, and be inſtructed all ye that are in places of authoritie in England, kiſs the Son leaſt he be angrie, and ye periſh from the way, <hi>when his wrath is kindled but a little.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.12.</note> Be wiſe ye rulers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and let it be your care to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the oppreſſed, and to judge the cauſe of the poor &amp; needy, and let juſtice and judgment take place with you, ſuffer not others to oppreſs, neither let it be found among you; Let not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the poor, and the ſighing of the needy, enter into the ears of the Lord of Sabboth againſt you; but execute judgment, and juſtice in your gates: ſo ſhall the kingdome be bleſſed and proſper.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be wiſe ye rulers, and ſeeing ye ſhould not beare the ſword in vaine, but for the puniſhment of evill doers; let the ſword of juſt puniſhment paſs againſt drunkards, whore-mongers, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, and ſwearers, and other vices: but I mention theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, becauſe on theſe the ſword of juſtice doth leaſt paſs; and theſe do moſt abound. O how may theſe be ſeen and heard in the ſtreets, and every corner of the City, &amp; little notice taken
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114255:4"/>of them, but they ſin with a face of braſs, and are neither afraid nor aſhamed; there being none, or few, that as <hi>Phinias</hi> did, do ſtand up and execute juſtice upon them. Let inſtice be done upon ſuch, that the judgments of God might be ſtayed, and the land may be ſafe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Be wiſe ye Rulers, and be inſtructed you Judges of England, and let Ieſus Chriſt raign over you; Caſt your Crowns at his feet, and ſubmit your ſelves to his royall and glorious Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and incroach not in the leaſt degree upon his preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, who as a King muſt only raign in the conſciences of his people, and govern them by his own Lawes: and therefore make you no Laws for the conſciences of his people, nor ſuffer any to do it by any authority derived from you; for that were to take the Crown off the head of Ieſus Chriſt, and put it on your own head; and thoſe people that ſhall ſubject their conſciences to thoſe Lawes, Chriſt Ieſus will ſay unto them,<note place="margin">Mark 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>In vain do you worſhip me, obſerving for Doctrines the commandements of men.</hi> O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beware how you ſubject your ſelves, or your people in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall worſhip to any rules, but thoſe that Ieſus Chriſt hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. Indeed ſuch as are judged to be truly godly men, may give adviſe and counſell therein: but upon no Terms im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their counſel as a Law upon conſciences, to whom the truth of it is dubious: nor ought they in the leaſt to deſpiſe one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, for not being of one minde in circumſtantials. This is the very rule of the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.3. <hi>Let not him that eateth, deſpiſe him that eateth not; nor let him that eateth not, deſpiſe him that eateth.</hi> Therefore kiſs the son with the kiſs of obedience, and ſubject your ſelves to his bleſſed government: ſo ſhall the bleſſings of his grace be poured out upon you.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Let it be your wiſdom to beware how you do of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend one of the little ones of Ieſus Chriſt, of whom he ſayes, <hi>It were better for a man to have a Mill-ſtone hanged about his neck &amp; to be caſt into the Sea, then to offend them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 2.8.</note> Beware therefore how you touch the Apple of Gods eye: let none of his Saints be wronged, or troubled by you: let them not be impriſoned or baniſhed by you; for they are the pillars of the Kingdom (in a ſence) if they be moved, the Kingdom will ſhake: if they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, the Kingdome will fall. O kiſs the Son with a kiſs of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114255:5"/>love, and expreſs your love to him, in loving his Saints, and ſo ſhall the kingdom be eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Be wiſe, and be ſure you do not ſtop the mouths of the Prophets of Ieſus Chriſt, commanding them to Preach no more in his name. Let it be far from you to do ſo, for if you ſhould do ſo, yet they cannot but ſpeak the things they have ſeen and heard; that viſion of Chriſt they have ſeen, and that voyce of the ſpirit they have heard, that they muſt ſpeak. If the Lyon hath roared, who will not fear? If the Lord hath ſpoken, who can but Propheſie? and if they be commanded the contrary, they muſt rather obey God then man: therefore be not fighters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God: do not kick againſt the Pricks. But if the Prophets and Preachers of Ieſus Chriſt abound in your Land, then ſhall you become a happy and glorious nation.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the paths, in which, if a kingdom walk, it will ſoon come into a happy eſtate and condition: but becauſe this laſt mentioned, which is of as high a concernment as any of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, may be probably moſt ſtumbled at; I ſhall endeavour to back it with the enſuing arguments. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. You that are the rulers of this Kingdom, do profeſs your ſelves to be the Subjects of Ieſus Chriſt, and to approve all his Commandments.<note place="margin">1 Cor 12.31.</note> 
               <hi>Now he commands all his to covet earneſtly the beſt gifts, but eſpecially that they may Propheſie.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. And this is ſpoken to all Saints whether they had been brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel</hi> or not. And what this Propheſying is, the Apoſtle ſhews in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.3. <hi>That it is ſpeaking to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, exhortation, and conſolation.</hi> And he makes no diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the exerciſe of this gift of the ſpirit, between an Officer of the Church and another; for he makes it to appear that any Member of the Church may exerciſe this gift, though none may execute the office of an Elder, but ſuch as are ordained thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, by the laying on of the hands of the Presbyterie: but ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of propheſying, ſaies the Apoſtle; <hi>Ye may all Propheſie one by one,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31. Now if you approve of the commands of the ſpirit of Jeſus Chriſt, who ſaies to all his Saints, covet to propheſie; how can you ſilence them when they ſo do?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let it be far from you ſo to do, for then you do endeavour to quench the ſpirit: for though you do permit ſome to Preach
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114255:5"/>Ieſus Chriſt, yet if you do prohibit any from Preaching Jeſus Chriſt, you do quench the ſpirit, and oppoſe the freeneſs of the ſpirit, who is a free Agent. And as the winde bloweth where it liſteth, though we ſee it not, ſo doth the ſpirit, and God hath not tyed himſelf to give out his ſpirit to ſuch particular men, and to no other, but to whom he pleaſes. He did not tie up the ſpirit of Propheſie in Law, neither to the Prieſts and Levites, nor the Prophets, nor the ſons of the Prophets; but gave out of that ſpirit to <hi>Amos</hi> a Heards-man, and to others: much leſs hath he tied up the ſpirit of Propheſying now in the Goſpel, unto ſuch and ſuch degrees of humane learning: for many learned, godly Miniſters have confeſſed, that they have learned many ſpiriutall truths of Ieſus Chriſt, from ſuch as have had no learning: and we know that Chriſt paſſed by the learned men in that time, &amp; choſe illiterate men to be his Apoſtles. Now for you to ſilence any that do preach Ieſus Chriſt, of what rank ſoever, it is an endeavor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to quench the ſpirit: which the Lord grant you may not do.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let it be far from you to hinder any, becauſe every tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent which the Lord Jeſus hath given, he requires an improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it to his uſe; and it ought not to lie hid in a napkin, and therefore the Apoſtle ſaies, <hi>Every gift is given to profit withall.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.7.</note> Now we know what the Lord ſaid to him that did not imploy his tallent. <hi>Caſt ye the unprofitable ſervant into utter darkneſs; there ſhall he weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, Math.</hi> 25.30. So fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is the doom of him that imployeth not his tallent: what then will become of thoſe that ſhall forbid any to imploy their tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents? But, O be you wiſe, and as you are Ordained of God to be, as for the puniſhment of evill doers, ſo for the praiſe of them that do well; ſo manifeſt your ſelves to be.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Do not you enact any law againſt any Saints exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing the gifts of the ſpirit, that are given to them in Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or propheſying: becauſe the Lord hath promiſed in the latter dayes, to power out his ſpirit more abundantly upon all fleſh, &amp; your ſons and your daughters ſhall propheſie: your old men ſhall dream dreams, and your young men ſhall ſee viſions, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. and the time of the accompliſhing of this promiſe more fully, is neer at hand: for the totall overthrow of Antichriſt and his finall ruin ſhall ſuddnely be; And then the everlaſting Goſpel ſhall be preached unto all nations, and kindreds, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114255:6"/>tongues, and people: and can any think that at that time the Lord will call forth none to this worke, but thoſe that have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſuch and ſuch degrees in the Schooles? Now what a ſad thing would it be, if when God ſhall call forth ſome of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to this great worke, any humane power ſhould ſtand in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to it, and ſay, ſuch and ſuch men ſhall not do ſuch a work.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Let it be far from you to forbid any man to preach the word of the Lord, becauſe his word doth good, it is ſtrong and powerfull in confirming, and comforting thoſe that are called; &amp; convincing, and converting thoſe that are uncalled, to make a people a holy and peculiar people to the Lord; you may ſee the force of this argument, in taking a view of a paſſage in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Micah. Mic:</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. In the 6. <hi>ver.</hi> we finde the Lord complaining againſt the people, in theſe words; Propheſie ye not, ſay they to them that propheſie. In the 7. <hi>ver.</hi> The Lord is ſpeaking thus: O thou that art named by the houſe of <hi>Iacob,</hi> is the ſpirit of the Lord ſtraitned? are theſe his doing? do not my words do good to them that walke uprightly? As if the Lord had ſaid, art thou the people that art named by the houſe of <hi>Iacob?</hi> and doſt thou ſay unto my Prophets, propheſie ye not? Thou ſhouldeſt have delighted in the words of the Prophets; for the houſe of <hi>Iacob</hi> have had experience that my words do good, and yet is the ſpirit of the Lord ſtraitned by you? and ſilence you it in my Prophets? Well, what was the iſſue of this? you ſhall ſee in the following verſe, and thus it was. My people are riſen up as an enemie, ye put off the robe with the garment from them that paſs by ſecurely. When the Prophets are forbidden to propheſie, and the word of the Lord is not preached among the people, then iniquity abounds, and the people periſh for want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: then every one doth that which his vaine heart leads him unto. But the word of the Lord converts the ſoule. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 19.7. And the truths of God ſanctifie the unholy, <hi>John.</hi> 17.17. and the word of God does good to them that walke uprightly, <hi>Mic.</hi> 2.6.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, though there be many precious men abroad, that by your permiſſion do preach the word, yet they are few in reſpect of the multitudes of people in the kingdome, that have none to preach unto them, and that cry for bread, but cannot have it:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114255:6"/>O therefore let it be far from you to ſtop the mouthes of any godly men, that have the gifts of ſpeaking to edification, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, and conſolation! and though they have not all taken degrees in the ſchooles of men, yet if they have been good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficients in the ſchoole of Chriſt, if they be experienced Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, let them be protected by your authoritie, in diſcharging their dutie, in improving their talents to their Maſters uſe and the kingdomes good, for the harveſt is great, but the labourers are few; therefore let not the labourers that God hath ſent forth, be forbidden to worke in the Lords Vineyard, leaſt the blood of thoſe that periſh be charged upon thoſe that hinder theſe labourers.</p>
            <p>But it may be objected; it is a truth indeed, that all Saints ought to covet the gift of propheſie; and ſecondly, it is an evill to quench the ſpirit; and 3 all ought to improve their talents; and 4 the abundant pourings out of the ſpirit are promiſed; and 5 the word of the Lord doth good; and 6 the labourers are few: and in theſe conſiderations it were a ſad thing to ſilence thoſe that are ſent forth by Jeſus Chriſt, furniſhed with the gifts of the ſpirit, for to preach the Goſpel. But if they ſhould be permitted to preach without ordination, who cannot ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto it by reaſon of ſcruples, though they are really Godly &amp; able men, then many that are erroneous perſons, &amp; erre groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, even in fundamentalls, would take libertie to goe and vent their errors among the people.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, erroneous perſons are not here pleaded for; but it is to be deſired that their mouths were ſtopped; but firſt, if none ſhould be permitted to preach but ſuch as were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, yet could not this hinder erroneous perſons from ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their errors, for thoſe that hold the groſſeſt errors, &amp; are the moſt notorious vile perſons, may, by making a faire compliance for the preſent, be admitted to Ordination, when afterward they may preach erroneous doctrine, and prove ſcandalous in their lives; and this is very evident: and though it be a trouble to thoſe that ordaine them, yet all the wiſdome of man cannot prevent it.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, it is a frequent thing for truth to be counted error by learned men, even by thoſe that have continually ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the letter of truth; it was ſo in our Saviours, and his Apoſtles
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114255:7"/>times: The high Preiſts, and all the Preiſts and Levits (whoſe lips ſhould preſerve knowledge, as the Prophet hath it) and all the learned Doctors of the Law, who ſtudied it continually, yet they counted the truths of Chriſt, and his Apoſties, which they made evident by Moſes, and the Prophets, to be errors.</p>
            <p>Nay 3. Not only learned men, but thoſe that are learned and really Godly men, may account ſome circumſtantiall truths (though not fundamentall) to be errors, and ſome errors to be truths, for though all that are reall Saints, are built upon one foundation, have one God and father, and one Lord Jeſus, and one faith, and one ſpirit, and one joy in that one ſpirit; yet thoſe that thus in the foundation agree in one, may yet exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly differ in circumſtances. They did ſo in the Apoſtles time, one is of <hi>Paul,</hi> another of <hi>Apollo,</hi> another of <hi>Cephas;</hi> One eatheth fleſh, another who is weake eateth hearbs;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.4</note> one obſerveth a day, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other obſerveth it not,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.2</note> and the Apoſtle in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11, 12. Implies, that it was poſſible for many errors to be built upon the true foundation (which he expreſſes by wood, hay, &amp; ſtubble) yet ſaies he, the perſon ſhall be ſaved, yet ſo as by fire, and every worke which is not of Chriſt ſhall be burnt, the fire of the ſpirit ſhall paſs upon it, and as wood, hay, and ſtubble is before the fire all combuſtible, ſo ſhall all error be, when it comes to indure the triall of the ſpirit, but truth only ſhall abide the triall of the fire of the ſpirit. Now if it were ſo in the Apoſtles times, that through imperfection in knowledge there were circumſtantiall errors amongſt the Saints, then it is no wonder if there be many more now, there having been ſuch an univerſall darknes ſpread over the world by the midnight of Poperie that hath been in the world: many of the clouds where of being yet remaining over the faces of Saints. Now if it be ſo, as it is cleere, that cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantiall errors may be in men built upon the true founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then thoſe men that are or ſhall be Ordainers (if they may be ſo called) may have errours; and ſo may account that Truth which is contrary to their errors to be error, when it is the truth it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I anſwer, we all expect the breakings forth of truth more &amp; more, &amp; no man can ſay they have yet attained to perfection. Now this truth may appeare to ſome before it doth to others. In ſome
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114255:7"/>Circumſtances it may appear to thoſe that are commonly called Presbyterians, before it doth to thoſe that are commonly call In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents: and in other Circumſtances it may appear to thoſe that are commonly called Independents, before it doth to Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians: And ſhall the Presbyterians deſpiſe the Independents, becauſe God (who doth what he pleaſes) hath not given them that light which they have obtained, and have the comfort of? Or ſhall the Independents deſpiſe the Presbyterians, becauſe God hath not given them that light which he hath conferred upon them, and they have the comfort of? Oh no! let it be far from either of them, ſeeing they are all built upon one foundation: but let them rather ſeriouſly conſider that paſſage of the Apoſtle, If any man be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal it to ſuch a one: if one man be otherwiſe minded and have not received that truth that appears to thee: It is not in his power of himſelf to receive it, nor in thy power to communicate it: But it is the Lord that muſt reveal it to him, or elſe he ſhall never receive it. And therefore if thou excelleſt thy brother in the knowledge of the truths of the Lord Jeſus in Doctrine or Diſcipline, conſider who it is that hath made thee to differ: What haſt thou, that thou haſt not received? and know, that that God that hath communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated ſo graciouſly to thee, may in his own time communicate more abundantly to thy brother, and thou thy ſelf mayeſt alſo ſee more hereafter then now thou doeſt, as thou now ſeeſt more then thou haſt ſeen, and this Age ſees more then the former Age.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We all condemn that Antichriſtian principle in Popery, to injoyn all to beleeve as the Church beleeves, that is, as the Pope and his Clergie, as their Lawes, and Decrees, and Canons requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, not ſuffering them to ſearch the Scriptures, and to ground their faith upon it. And we had indeed juſt cauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it, and to deteſt it, for though men ſhould teach nothing but the truth of Chriſt, and people ſhould receive it; yet if they receive it but from men, and have not the word of God, and the ſpirit of God witneſſing the truth of that which is preached un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, though they might receive the Letter of truth, they yet could not receive the truth in truth, and ſo might periſh not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding: therefore whatſoever appears to another to be a truth, yet if it doth not appear from the word to thee to be a truth, thou art not to practiſe it. And,</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:114255:8"/>
            <p n="6">6. I anſwer, as for erroneous perſons, we ought to uſe no other weapons againſt them, then what the Apoſtles did: they preached againſt them, &amp; held forth the truth for the conviction of them, but uſed no other way; nor did Chriſt nor his Apoſtles ſpeak of any other way: but ſay they, the weapons of our warfare are not carnal, but mighty: for if it were required that the Civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate by any power or force, beſides that which the Goſpel al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of, ſhould go about to ſuppreſs them, then might they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs truth inſtead of errour. The civil Magiſtrates being but men, may judge a truth to be an errour through their imperfection in knowledge, and ſo may commend errour inſtead of truth, and condemn truth inſtead of errour.</p>
            <p n="7">7. If there be a ſpirit of errour upon any, and they erre in fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals, not knowing Jeſus Chriſt, nor having received his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and they go forth and vent their errours after all Goſpel-means uſed, we are to leave them to the juſt judgement of God, who hath revealed, that he will inflict his Judgements upon them. As <hi>Micah</hi> 3.5, 6, 7. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, concerning the Prophets that make my people erre, that bite with their teeth, and cry peace; and he that putteth not into their mouths, they even prepare war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: Therefore night ſhall be upon them, &amp;c.</hi> To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there are ſeverall other paſſages in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and other of the Prophets. And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of falſe Teachers that ſhall be among the people, ſayes he, <hi>They ſhall bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction, for their Judgement lingereth not, and their damnation ſlumbereth not,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2, 3 And ſaies <hi>Paul, If any man love not our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let him be</hi> Anathema Maranatha. I could deſire if there were any rule clearly revealed for it, that the civill Magiſtrate might ſo reſtrain them, as they might not ſpeak a word to any man all their daies: but ſeeing not how far the Civil Magiſtrate hath a ſure rule for this, I turn this deſire into a prayer, to the great Magiſtrate of the whole world, the great God, humbly deſiring that he would make all his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable enemies as a wheel, and as ſtubble before the winde; and that he would ſo giude the civill Magiſtrate in all his affairs, that under him all the Saints of God may live a quiet and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able life in all godlineſs and honeſty: So much in anſwer to that Objection: but ſeeing it is preſented as the way to happineſs,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114255:8"/>to protect from all wrong and violence, the Saints of Jeſus Chriſt, and to beware of impriſoning or baniſhing of them, leaſt the Kingdom come to ruine; it may be quaeried who are thoſe Saints of Ieſus Chriſt that are unto him as the Apple of his eye? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, they are not confin'd to any particular ſociety of men, that are diſtinguiſhed by ſuch or ſuch a title, as <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Anabaptiſts, Independents, Seekers, &amp;c.</hi> and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be defined by any ſuch title, as to ſay, only ſuch as are Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians are the Saints of Ieſus Chriſt, or only ſuch as are Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, are the Saints of Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor are they all Saints that are diſtinguiſhed by any of theſe titles; for many that profeſs themſelves to be for the Presbyterian way, are very ſcandalous perſons, and the Author of the Gangraena might have had as plentifull inſtances of ſcandalous perſons among thoſe, as any of the reſt, and that upon as unqueſtionable evidences, had he dealt impartially in that work; and many of the way called Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie, have been very ſcandalous alſo, and ſo of the reſt: and yet among all theſe which have ſeverall titles, there are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly many reall Saints, ſo that we cannot ſay ſuch a one is not a Saint, becauſe he is not a Presbyterian, an Independent, or an Anabaptiſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But who are Saints, and who are not, is moſt viſible to him that knoweth all things.</p>
            <p>But if you would be ſure to deal well with all the Saints of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, then deal well with all them that do hold the head, do acknowledge God the Father to be true God, and Jeſus Chriſt to be the ſon of God, the brightneſs of his glory, and the expreſs Image of his perſon; and that this Ieſus Chriſt is the Saviour, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and the Juſtifier of all that truly beleeve on his name, and that there is no other name under heaven whereby men may be ſaved, but by this Jeſus: and that he is the great King, Prieſt, and Prophet of his people, and that from the Father and the Son proceedeth the holy ſpirit, which teacheth, comforteth, &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifieth the Saints. I ſay, if a man do acknowledge theſe things, which are the foundations, upon which Chriſt hath built his Church, and if his walking be not ſcandalous, whatſoever ſuch a mans judgement may be in circumſtantiall things, if any one ſhould condemn ſuch in ſo doing, he might condemn thoſe whom God hath juſtified, and offend the generation of his children. But all thoſe that ſo acknowledge the true foundation, which is the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114255:9"/>foundation of all the Apoſtles and Prophets, ought by you to be protected, and not to be deprived of their liberties and priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as they are ſubjects, whatſoever their judgements be in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantials; but if any of theſe offend in being drunkards, ſwearers, whoremongers, <hi>&amp;c,</hi> let them ſuffer according to the fact; but as long as they walk holily in their lives, beware how you fall upon them, leaſt they prove a burthenſom ſtone unto you, and in falling upon them you be broken in peices<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But if (as God forbid) the civill Magiſtrate ſhould be ſo far perſwaded by the lovers of diſcords, and enemies of peace, as to impriſon, puniſh, baniſh, or turn out of the world ſome of them, it ſhould do them no hurt, for they ſhould loſe nothing by whatſoever they ſuffer, but receive an hundred fold; but thoſe that do it, would be in far better caſe, if they were ſufferers, then Actors.</p>
            <p>Nor if while it is called to day, this ſeaſonable word ſhall be received, it may poſſibly prevent the breakings out of another fire of wrath, which otherwiſe, may ſuddenly break out upon this kingdom. If now this cordiall ſhall be received, it may allay the violence of (&amp; expell) that diſtemper which is upon this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which otherwiſe may prove its death. Now it muſt be firſt taken in by the head, by thoſe that are in higheſt Authority, and from thence the ſweet and comfortable effects of it ſhall deſcend to all the members, the whole body, to the ſtrengthening and heightening of it, &amp; making of it famous among all the nations.</p>
            <p>Many other things might be ſpoken by way of motive, and clearing ſome other objections, but to an underſtanding people it is ſuperfluous. The things herein propoſed being ſo clear, as that few or none that love the truth and peace will, or can op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
